Guide to the World War I Posters File [1914]-1920 PR 55-7
New-York Historical Society
World War I Poster File
[1914]-1920
1917-1918
New-York Historical Society
PR 55-7
1.45 Linear feet (ca. 1200 posters)
Collection of posters, pictorial sheets, and related ephemera, [1914]-1920, used by governments and organizations during World War I to persuade citizens to enlist in various branches of the armed services, buy bonds, conserve food and fuel, provide relief, and generally support the war effort
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research; access requires at least 24 hours advance notice.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into series:
Series I: Recruitment
Series II: Monetary Appeals
Series III: Patriotic Appeals
Series IV: Conservation Appeals
Series V: Relief Appeals
Series VI: Organizational
Series VII: Miscellaneous
Scope and Contents Note
The World War I Poster File, which forms part of the larger Poster File (PR-055), dates from circa 1914 to 1920, and consists of posters, pictorial sheets and related ephemera used by governments and organizations during the first World War to persuade citizens to enlist in various branches of the armed service, buy bonds, conserve food and fuel, provide relief, and generally support the war and aid efforts. Included in the collection is Montgomery Flagg's famous "I Want You" poster; also included are posters by Howard Chandler Christy, Alonzo Earl Foringer, Wladyslaw T. Benda, Fortunino Matania, Charles Dana Gibson, and Joseph Pennell. This series of the Poster File is divided into seven subseries: Recruitment, Monetary Appeals, Patriotic Appeals, Conservation Appeals, Relief Appeals, Organizational, and Miscellaneous.
Arrangement Note
Posters are arranged by subject.
Historical Note
Posters were an established means of communication well before World War I, and although traditional media were also used, the unrivalled ability of posters to communicate quickly and memorably allowed governments and organizations to persuade and inform the public on matters of public policy and mobilize the home front. Posters were used for recruiting, fund-raising, to bolster support, to encourage industrial output, and to support a variety of relief efforts. Patriotism and a sense of duty were captured in visual metaphor by a variety of popular graphic artists.
In the United States, poster campaigns were especially well supported, popular, and extensive during the first World War. Many prominent American illustrators donated their services to the federal government under the auspices of the Division of Pictorial Publicity, through the leadership of Charles Dana Gibson. Illustrators used a wide range of styles, from iconic images and historical art references to glamour girls and cartoons.
Provenance
Posters are from a variety of purchases and gifts.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Finance -- United States -- Posters.; Lithographs.; Posters.; Prints (visual works).; Savings bonds -- United States.; War posters, American.; War posters, British; World War, 1914-1918 -- Civilian relief; World War, 1914-1918 -- Economic aspects -- United States.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Moral and ethical aspects; World War, 1914-1918 -- Posters.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects -- United States.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- Children; Flagg, James Montgomery, 1877-1960; Christy, Howard Chandler, 1873-1952; Benda, Wladyslaw T. (Wladyslaw Theodore), 1873-1948; American Red Cross -- Public relations.; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A -- Public relations; Young Men's Christian associations -- Public relations; United states. War Production Board -- Posters; United States. Army -- Recruiting, enlistment, etc. -- World War, 1914-1918; Foringer, A. E. (Alonzo Earl), 1878-1948
- Series I: Recruitment, 1
  Scope and Contents Note
  Series I: Recruitment, includes posters used to encourage enlistment in the United States Army, Air Force, Marines, Navy, Tank Corps, American Field Service, a variety of local and state regiments, and the National Guard. Also present in this series are draft notices and other materials produced by the Selective Service Draft Board, such as draft notices in French, Russian, Czech, Polish, and Italian among others.
  - Subseries I.1: US Army / Air Force, 1
    - Join Army / Navy / Marines (Folder 1)
      General note
      US Flag with tassles
    - Join Army/Navy/Marines (Folder 1)
      U.S. flag
    - US Army / 50,000 redblooded men going to serve in France and on the Rhine now / US Recruiting Station in Maine / Portland, 463 Congress St (Folder 1)
    - For liberty (Folder 1)
      Soldier/sailor crossing guns/Statue of Liberty background
    - The United States Army/ Wants men/ Between 18 and 35 years of age/A steady job 3 to 30 years/Retirement at the end of 30 years with a check each month for $33.00 to $79.50 for life. Apply recruiting offices (Various addresses in NYC) (Folder 1)
      Soldier on horseback
    - The United States Army/ Wants men/ Between 18 and 35 years fo age/Board, lodging, clothing, baths, gymnasium/Bowling alleys/School/LibrariesFree Apply Army recruiting offices25 Third Ave, 147 Park Row, 749 Sixth Ave... (Folder 1)
      Soldier
    - One hundred drafted colored men/Who drilled with Dr. Boyce before joining the Buffaloes, are in position of authority in their regiments now/Address all communications for Dr. Boyce's Military Free Night Schoos (Boyce's Tigers) to Dr. A.L. Boyce..., 1917 (Folder 1)
      cartoon strip: "colored" soldiers, 2 menials & 1 corporal who had trained with Dr. Boyce
    - The U.S. Air Service needs/Carpenters/Cabinet makers & wood workers/See U.S. Army recruiting office at /Before December 13 (Folder 1)
    - Uphold our honor/Join ArmyNavyMarines (Folder 1)
      American flag
    - The U.S. Air Service needs/Machinists/And metal workers/See U.S. Army recruiting office at/142 East 14 St/Before December 13 (Folder 1)
      photographs of Pershing, battle scenes
    - Serve on the Rhine Now in the A.E.F. / United States Recruiting Station in Maine / Portland, 463 Congress St (Folder 1)
      Uncle Sam and civilian
    - "Fellows who stick by you in everything" says Corporal Daly (Folder 1)
    - The air service wants 1000 New England men at once(Listing of recruiting offices in Massachusetts) (Folder 1)
    - Join Army / Navy / Marines (Folder 1)
      US Flag
    - Join Army/Navy/Marines (Folder 1)
      U.S. flag with tassels
    - The father of our country / Appealed for soldiers as follows.. .. .. / Do as our forefathers did in 1776 / Enlist / Army Recruiting Office (Folder 1)
      Replicas of Continental Army soldiers and quote from Washington broadside
    - The United States Army /Wants men / Between 18 and 35 years of age / Board, lodging, clothing, baths, gymnasium / Bowling alleys / School / Libraries Free apply / Army Recruiting Offices 25 Third Ave, 147 Park Row, 749 Sixth Ave, 79 Cortland St, .. ... (Folder 1)
    - The United States Army /Wants men / Between 18 and 35 years of age / A steady job 3 to 30 years / Retirement at the end of 30 years with a check each month for $33.00 to $79.50 for life. Apply Recruiting Offices (+various addresses NYC) (Folder 1)
      Soldiers on horseback
    - Uphold our honor / Join the army navy marines (Folder 1)
    - One hundred drafted colored men / Who drilled with Dr Boyce before joining the Buffaloes are in position of authority in their regiments now / Address all communications for Dt Boyce's Military Free Night Schools (Boyce's Tigers) to Dr AL Boyce Box 23..., 1917 (Folder 1)
      Cartoon: 3 stereotypically drawn "colored" soldiers; 2 menialists, 1 corporal who announces his attendance to Dr Boyce's
    - The U.S. Air Service needs / Machinists / And metal workers / See US Army Recruiting Office at / 142 East 14 St (in crayon) / Before December 13 (Folder 1)
    - The U.S. Air Service needs / Carpenters / Cabinet makers and wood workers / See US Army Recruiting Office at ____________ /Before December 13 (Folder 1)
    - The Air Service wants 1000 New England men at once (listing of recruiting offices in MA) (Folder 1)
    - The sun never sets on the stars and stripes / The US Army gives you your choice.. .. .. An education in intself / See the US Army Recruiting and Office at ____ (various addresses in Maine / NH) (Folder 1)
    - The Army / You'll like it / Do you want a University Education? / Uncle Sam will pay for it / US Army Recruiting Stations Maine / New Hampshire (Folder 1)
    - Pershing wants 12,000 real men / Will you be one of them? / Serve your country with the skill that is yorus (Folder 1)
    - Volunteer / And choose your own branch of the service / Uncle Sam (Folder 1)
      Uncle Sam
    - For liberty (Folder 1)
      Soldier, sailor crossing guns; Statue of Liberty background
    - The father of our country/Appealed for soldiers as follows…/DO as our forefathers did in 1776/Enlist/Army recruiting office (Folder 1)
      replicas of Continental Army soldiers & quote from Washington broadside
    - The sun never sets on the Stars & Stripes/The U.S. Army gives you your choice... An education in itself/See the U.S. Army recruiting officeer at (various locations in Maine/New Hampshire) (Folder 1)
    - U.S. Army/50,000 redblooded men going to serve in France and on the Rhinenow/U.S. recruiting station in Maine/Portland, 463 Congress St. (Folder 1)
    - Serve on the Rhinenow in the A.E.F./United States recruiting station in Maine/Portland, 463 Congress St. (Folder 1)
    - The Army/You'll like it/Do you want a University Education?/Uncle Sam will pay for it/U.S. Army recruiting stations Maine/New Hampshire (Folder 1)
    - Pershing want 12,000 real men/Will you be one of them?/Serve your country with the skill that is yours (Folder 1)
    - Volunteer/And choose your own branch of the service/Uncle Sam (Folder 1)
    - Join the Army Air Service/Be an American Eagle! (Folder 2)
      Warring American Eagles (American/German)
    - "New York City has at present no protection against hostile aircraft. Such protection is an immediate and present necessity." John Dorroy Mitchell, mayor./Veteran Corps of Artillery/Armory: 33 Street and Park Ave./Enlist now. (Folder 2)
      soldier scanning sky for bombs to bridge
    - Join the Air Service and serve in France/Do it now, 1917 (Folder 2)
      2 soldiers and fighter plane
    - Roll of Honor/of our men who have entered the service of their country by joining the Army or Navy/Contributed by the Vigilantes (Folder 2)
      Blank "honor roll" with American Eagle above
    - Columbia calls / Enlist now for US Army (Folder 2)
      "Liberty " carrying flag and Halsted poem of 1916
    - Columbia calls/Enlist now for U.S. Army (Folder 2)
      "Liberty" carrying flag and Halsted poem of 1916
    - Enlist/On which side of the window are you?, 1917 (Folder 2)
      Civilian looking out window at parade of soldiers
    - 500 Teamsters/Wanted for the Army/Recruiting office: 357 Broadway, N.Y. City (Folder 2)
      Soldiers and horse-drawn cart
    - U.S. Army Air Service need men / Chauffeurs, mechanics and allied tradesmen are especially desired / come on / Help win the war (Folder 2)
    - New York City has at present no protection against hostile aircraft. Such protection is an immediate and present necessity." John Durroy Mitchel, Mayor / Veteran Corps of Artillery / Armory 33 Street and Park Ave / Enlist now (Folder 2)
    - Enlist / On which side of the the window are you?, 1917 (Folder 2)
      Civliain looking out window at parade of soldiers
    - Join the Army Air Service / Be an American Eagle (Folder 2)
      Warring eagles (American and German)
    - Join the Air Service and serve in France / Do it now, 1917 (Folder 2)
    - Roll of Honor / of our men who have entered the service of their country by joining the army or navy / Contributed by the Vigilantes (Folder 2)
      Blank "honor roll" with American eagle above
    - 500 Teamsters / Wanted for the Army / Recruiting Office, 357 Boradway, NYC (Folder 2)
      Soldiers and horse drawn cart
    - U.S. Army Air Service need men/Chauffeurs, mechanics and allied tradesmen are especially desired/Come on/Help win the war (Folder 2)
  - Subseries I.2: Marines, 2
    - U.S. Pictoral Service / Ruth Law wants to fly with US Marines / New Orleans, 1917 (Folder 3)
      Ruth Law on plane, marines, 1 carrying recruitment poster by LA Shafer
    - U.S. Pictoral Service / Charley Chaplin, Douglas Fairbanks and Mary Pickford / Do their bit to help the USMarine Corps recruit men, 1918 (Folder 3)
      Photo and illustration of above
    - U.S. Pictoral Service / Big Jess Willard enlists with US Marines, 1917 (Folder 3)
      Photo of Big Jess Willard
    - Go over with US Marines, 1918 (Folder 3)
      Lady Marine calendar for July 1918
    - US Pictorial Service/Ruth Law wants to fly with U.S. Marines/New Orleans, 1917 (Folder 3)
      Ruth Law (aviatrix) on plane, Marines, 1 carrying recruitment poster by L.A Shafer
    - Proclamation! / Citizens of New York / You are going to enlist .. .. .. Marines Corps / 24 East 23 St, Signed George Banint (?) (Folder 3)
    - Join me / The first to fight on land and sea / US Marines / Apply at 24 East 23 Street, NYC (Folder 3)
      Head of marine with rifle (hat cut off)
    - U.S. Pictoral Service / Giant artillery tractor used by US Marines / Quantico, VA, 1918 (Folder 3)
      Photo of above
    - US Marines / Serve America on land and sea / Enlist at 2 East 23 St, NY (Folder 3)
      Marine marching on poer, battleship in rear
    - Your country calls / Join the Marines / For information apply recruiting station or Navy League (Folder 3)
    - "All in the day's work" / Enlist in the United States Marine Corps for interesting duty land, sea or sky (Folder 3)
      Cartoon of marines in different activities
    - Chasing the rainbow / While encircling the globe / Men wanted for a good job / United States Recruiting Station / Ask the Postmaster (Folder 3)
      Photos of marines in various countries and various activities
    - For action on sea and land / Join the Marines / Apply at US Marine Recruiting Station / 24 East 23 Street, New York (Folder 3)
    - Join me/The first to fight on land and sea/US Marines/Apply at 24 East 23rd Street, New York City (Folder 3)
      head of Marine with rifle (hat cut off)
    - U.S. Marines/Serve America on land and sea/Enlist at 24 East 23rd St., New York (Folder 3)
      Marine marching on pier/battleship in rear
    - Go over with U.S. Marines, 1918 (Folder 3)
      lady Marine/calendar for July 1918
    - U.S. Pictorial Service/Charley Chaplin, Douglas Fairbanks and Mary Pickford/Do their bit to help the US Marine Corps Recruitment, 1918 (Folder 3)
      photo and illustration by Hadley/Marine Corps
    - All in the day's work/Enlist in the United States Marine Corps for interesting duty land, sea, or sky. (Folder 3)
      Cartoon of Marines in different activities
    - Proclamation!/Citizens of New York/You are going to enlist... Marine Corps./24 East 23 St. signed George Banint? (Folder 3)
    - Chasing the rainbow/While encircling the globe/Men wanted for a good job/United States Recruiting Station/Ask the Postmaster (Folder 3)
      photos of Marines in various countries/various activities
    - For action on sea and land/Join the Marines/Apply at U.S. Marine Recruiting Station, 24 East 23 Street, New York (Folder 3)
    - U.S. Pictorial Service/Big Jess Willard enlists with U.S. Marines, 1917 (Folder 3)
      photo of Big Jess Willard
    - Your country calls/Join the Marines/For information apply recruiting station or Navy League (Folder 3)
    - U.S. Pictorial Service/Giant artillery tractor used by U.S. Marines/Quantico, VA., 1918 (Folder 3)
      photot of giant artillery tractor
    - First in France/U.S. Marines (Folder 4)
      charging Marine
    - First in France / U.S. Marines (Folder 4)
      Charging marine
    - The US Marines / Want you / Apply at 24 East 23 Street, NYC (Folder 4)
      US Marine
    - He did his duty / "No finer military organization than the Marine Corps exists in the world" George Dewey, Admiral of the Navy / Will you? / Join.. .. .. US Marines Apply at 139 Bowery, NY, NY (Folder 4)
    - Do your duty / Join the US Marines / Help them defend America on land and sea / Apply at / 24 East 23 Street, NY, NY (Folder 4)
      Marines among cannon on ship
    - Marine Corps Week / June 10 16 / Join the U.S. Marines / The soldiers that go to sea / Where there's action / Enlist at 24 East 23 St, NY (Folder 4)
      Marines standing at attention on board ship
    - Teufel Hunden / German nickname for the U.S. Marines / Devil Dog Recruiting Station / 628 South State Street (Folder 4)
      Hefty fiery-eyed bulldog with US helmet chasing cute little German helmeted dachshund
    - First to fight! U.S. Marines / Enlist at 24 East 23 St (Folder 4)
    - U.S. Marines / Soldiers of the sea (Folder 4)
      Marines attacking with bayonets
    - For active Service Join the U.S. Marines / For full information apply to Postmaster (Folder 4)
      2 marines on ledge overlooking battleships, 1 with binoculars, 1 with samaphone
    - "Spirit of 1917" / Join the U.S. Marines at 8 Fourth Avenue, Brooklyn, N.Y. (Folder 4)
      4 Marines carry US Flag and Marine Corps flag
    - EEEYahYip / Go over with U.S. Marines (Folder 4)
      Marine with bayonet
    - US Marines / Fist to hoist old glory on foreign soil /Join them for overseas duty / Enlist at 24 East 23 St. (Folder 4)
      Marines hoisting American flag on sunny land with palm tree thatched roof houses
    - U.S. Marines/Soldiers of the sea (Folder 4)
    - The U.S. Marines/Want you/Apply at 24 East 23rd Street, New York City (Folder 4)
      U.S. Marine facing you
    - He did his duty/"No finer military organization than the Marine Corps exists in the world." George Dewey, Admiral of the Navy/Will you?/Join... US Marines. Apply at 139 Bowery, New York, NY (Folder 4)
      Admiral Dewey
    - Do your duty/Join the U.S. Marines/Help them defend America on land and sea/Apply at/24 East 23 Street, New York, NY (Folder 4)
      Marines arming cannon on ship
    - Marine Corps week/June 10 to 16/Join the U.S. Marines/The soldiers that go to sea/Where there's action/Enlist at 24 East 23 Street, New York (Folder 4)
    - Teufel Hunden/German nickname for US Marines/Devil dog Recruiting Station/628 South State Street (Folder 4)
      bulldog with US helmet chasing German helmeted dachschund
    - First to fight! US Marines/Enlist at 24 East 23rd St. (Folder 4)
    - US Marines/First to hoist Old Glory on foreign soil/Join them for overseas duty/Enlist at 24 East 23 Street (Folder 4)
      Marines hoisting American flag on sunny land with palm tree & thatched-roof houses
    - "Spirit of 1917"/Join the U.S. Marines at Fourth Avenue, Brooklyn, NY (Folder 4)
      4 Marines carry US flag & Marine Corps flag
    - "Soldiers of the Sea"/Write for illustrated booklet/Headquarters US Marine Corps, Washington DC (Folder 4)
      2 Marines in full dress standing next to plinth with Marine Corps symbol. 1 with bugle, 1 with gun
    - EEEYahYip/Go over with U.S. Marines (Folder 4)
    - "Soldiers of the Sea" / Write for illustrated booklet / Headquarters US Marine Corps, Washington DC (Folder 4)
      2 marines standing next to plinth with marin Corps symbol; 1 with bugle, 1 with gun
    - For active service join the U.S. Marines/For full information apply to Postmaster (Folder 4)
      2 marines on ledge overlooking battleships, 1 with binoculars, 1 with semaphore
  - Subseries I.3: Navy, 3
    - Halt the hun/Submarine/Clear the road to france/Join the Navy, Naval Reserve or Coast Guard. One Service/One Call (Folder 5)
      men, women, children huddled on lifeboat, sailor pointing to rescue ship
    - The Navy strikes now/Follow the flag for freedom/Your choice, Naval Reserve, Coast Guard, or Navy/394 E. 150th Street (Folder 5)
      "Liberty" leading the navy
    - For liberty's sake/Enlist in the Navy (Folder 5)
      Statue of Liberty
    - U.S. Navy needs Americans man the battle fleet/Enlist at 962 Chapel St., 1917 (Folder 5)
    - See the world! Save your money! Serve the nation! Navy/Information gladly give at U.S. Navy recruiting stations (Folder 5)
      sailor pointing to sign
    - U.S. Navy/It is hereby directed that the authorized enlisted strength of the Navy be increased to 87,000 men. Woodrow Wilson./Make this a new leaf; turn it over and see what you ought to do., 1917 (Folder 5)
      Uncle Sam beckoning civilians to enlist
    - U.S.S. Recruit, "launched" in Union Square, NYC, May 30, 1917/Crowd of civilians visit the dreadnaught daily (Folder 5)
      photo of above
    - First call/I need you in the Navy this minute!/Our country will always be proudest of those who answered the first call/Navy Recruiting Stations: 34 East 23rd Street, NY/ 115 Flatbush Ave., Brooklyn, 1917 (Folder 5)
      Uncle Sam pointing to you
    - Warding off a night attack / Each dread naught carries 20 mor more 5inch rapid fire guns for repelling the attacks of topedo vessels / These guns are loaded and fired 20 times per minute and have a 60 pound projectile at 2 miles off (Folder 5)
      Photo of sailors manning a gun aboard a ship
    - Warding off a night attack/Each dreadnaught carriers 20 or more 5inch rapid fire guns repelling the attacks of torpedo vessels/These guns are loaded and fired 20 times per minute and hurl a 60 pound projectile at a target 2 Miles off.." (Folder 5)
      photo of sailors manning a gun aboard ship
    - Army and Navy/A lift as far as we go (Folder 5)
    - Greatest school on earth/Travel in the United States Navy and Learn to Know the World You Live In/Ages 17 to 35 Years/Apply Navy Recruiting Station (Folder 5)
      Photo of battleship at sea
    - A good Navy must have the best men/Don't delay/ Enlist today, 1917 (Folder 5)
      All Print and Navy Seal
    - Your Navy needs you now/Enlist/at the nearest Recruiting Station, 1917 (Folder 5)
      All Print and Navy Department Seal
    - Navy! Uncle Sam is calling you! Enlist in the Navy! Do it now/I want you, 1917 (Folder 5)
    - The Navy League / Has the honor of announcing, that this house has furnished a man for the nation's defense (Folder 5)
      Printed message below US Navy League flag
    - The Navy League/Has the honor of announcing, that this house has furnished a man for the nation's defense (Folder 5)
      printed message below U.S. Navy League flag
    - Army and Navy / A lift as far as we go (Folder 5)
    - Greatest School on earth / Travel in the United States Navy and learn to know the world you live in / Ages 17 to 35 years / Apply Navy Recruiting Station (Folder 5)
    - A good navy must have the best men / Don't delay / Enlist today, 1917 (Folder 5)
      Navy Dept seal
    - Your Navy needs you now / Enlist / At the nearest recruiting station, 1917 (Folder 5)
    - Keep the American Flag on the seas/Join the Navy/Enlist now Your country needs you (Folder 5)
      battleships on high seas
    - Torpedo Boat destroys passing in review, 1917 (Folder 5)
    - U.S.S. Recruit, "Launched" in Union Square, NYC May 30, 1917 / Crowd of civilians visit the Dreadnaught daily (Folder 5)
    - Protect your flag / Navy needs you / Apply Recruitiment Station or Navy League, 1917 (Folder 5)
      Flags of Britain, US, France; sailor with HMS hat and sailor with FRANCE on hat
    - Will you supply eyes for the Navy? Navy Ships need binoculars and spy glasses / Will you help us "stand watch" on a destroyer (Folder 5)